<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<c74object name="tap.overdrive~" module="msp" category="TapTools, MSP Distortion">

	<digest>
		Voiced feedback overdrive / saturation
	</digest>

	<description>
		The <o>tap.overdrive~</o> object is a soft-clipping overdrive whose nonlinearity sits
		inside a lowpass feedback loop — the topology of TS-lineage feedback pedals (voiced
		against the Mad Professor Little Green Wonder) — rather than a static waveshaping curve
		applied to the whole spectrum. The result is frequency-dependent clipping: bass stays
		tight and nearly clean at any drive while mids and highs take the full gain and break up
		first, and the tilt grows as the drive rises. The asymmetry attribute biases the clipper
		for even-harmonic warmth (a built-in DC blocker removes the offset this creates), and a
		unity clean path is summed around the clipper so the transfer keeps rising with reduced
		slope instead of flattening into a hard digital plateau. The body attribute is the
		signature voicing control: toward -1 fuller lows reach the clipper and the top gets a
		slight lift; toward +1 the lows tighten and thin and the upper mids push forward. The
		clipping stage runs oversampled (default 4x) to keep aliasing down, and all parameters
		glide smoothly. This object is the spiritual successor to the original Jamoma-era
		tap.overdrive~, replacing its memoryless waveshaper modes. Single-channel: wrap in mc.
		for multichannel.
	</description>


	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">74 Objects</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">TapTools</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Audio</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Distortion</metadata>
	</metadatalist>


	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="clear">
			<arglist/>
			<description>Reset the filter, feedback, and resampler state.</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>


	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="drive" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Drive (0-1). 0 is edge-of-breakup — a pedal's gain knob full
			counterclockwise, still warm — and 1 is heavily saturated. The sweep is perceptual
			(dB of gain into the clipper); use bypass for a true clean signal.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="body" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Body voicing (-1..+1, 0 neutral). Toward -1: fuller lows into the
			clipper and a slight treble lift. Toward +1: thinner, tighter lows and an upper-mid
			push. Linear pre/post voicing around the clipper, not part of the
			nonlinearity.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="asymmetry" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Asymmetry (0-1): even-harmonic amount. 0 is a symmetric clip (odd
			harmonics only); raising it biases the clipper for even-order warmth. The DC this
			generates is removed by the built-in DC blocker.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="preamp" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Input gain in dB (-24..24), applied before the clipper.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="output" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Makeup gain in dB (-24..24), applied at the output.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="oversample" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<description>Internal oversampling factor for the clipping stage (1, 2, 4, or 8;
			default 4). Reduces aliasing from the clipper's harmonics.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="smooth" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Anti-zipper interpolation time in milliseconds applied to parameter changes.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="bypass" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<description>Pass the input through unprocessed.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="mute" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<description>Silence the output.</description>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>


	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="overdrive~"/>
		<seealso name="tap.vca~"/>
		<seealso name="tap.svf~"/>
		<seealso name="tap.dcblock~"/>
	</seealsolist>


</c74object>
