<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<c74object name="tap.303~" module="msp" category="TapTools, MSP Synthesis">

	<digest>
		TB-303-style acid bass voice
	</digest>

	<description>
		The <o>tap.303~</o> object is a monophonic acid bass voice modeled on the Roland
		TB-303: a sawtooth or square oscillator into the diode-ladder filter (the same kernel
		as <o>tap.diode~</o>), shaped by the 303's two envelopes — the decay-only Main
		Envelope sweeping the cutoff (envmod, with the hardware's law: two thirds of the
		sweep above the cutoff knob, one third below) and the fixed-decay VCA envelope
		(fast attack, ~1.2 s decay, no sustain, chopped at gate-off). Accented notes hit
		louder with a faster envelope, scaled by the accent knob — and drive the 303's
		accent-sweep circuit: a capacitor charges with each accent and pushes the cutoff
		higher when accents come close together (the famous build-up), scaled by the
		resonance knob and independent of envmod. Pitch arrives in the left
		inlet as a MIDI note number (signal, read per sample, or float; fractions are
		cents). The right inlet is a gate signal whose rising edge triggers the note —
		<b>edge amplitude encodes accent</b>: 1.0 is a plain note, up to 2.0 fully
		accented. Slide is legato, exactly like the hardware: change the pitch while the
		gate is held and it glides through the 303's ~60 ms lag without retriggering — no
		separate slide input. The note/bang/release messages provide the same control
		without signals. Envelope constants and the filter's feedback behavior follow
		measured hardware values (via the Open303 project and the Devil Fish
		documentation). One voice per object; wrap in mc. for polyphony.
	</description>


	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">74 Objects</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">TapTools</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Audio</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Synthesis</metadata>
	</metadatalist>


	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="float">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="pitch" type="float" optional="0" id="0" />
			</arglist>
			<description>In the left inlet, sets the pitch (MIDI note number). The next
			trigger plays it; if the gate is currently held, the voice slides there now.</description>
		</method>
		<method name="note">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="pitch" type="float" optional="0"/>
				<arg name="accent" type="int" optional="1"/>
				<arg name="slide" type="int" optional="1"/>
			</arglist>
			<description>Play a note: pitch in MIDI note numbers, accent 0/1, slide 0/1.
			With slide 1 and a note already sounding, the pitch glides legato instead of
			retriggering.</description>
		</method>
		<method name="bang">
			<arglist/>
			<description>Retrigger the last note (plain, no accent).</description>
		</method>
		<method name="release">
			<arglist/>
			<description>Release the gate — the VCA chops, like the hardware's gate-off.</description>
		</method>
		<method name="store">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="slot" type="int" optional="0"/>
			</arglist>
			<description>Store the current parameters in a preset slot (1-16).</description>
		</method>
		<method name="recall">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="slot" type="int" optional="0"/>
				<arg name="time" type="float" optional="1"/>
			</arglist>
			<description>
				Morph all parameters to a stored preset (1-16). The optional second argument
				overrides the morph time in milliseconds (default: the interp attribute).
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="clear">
			<arglist/>
			<description>Silence the voice and reset all DSP state.</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>


	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="cutoff" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Filter cutoff knob in Hz (100-5000; the stock 303 knob spans
			~302-2394 — the wider range is the Devil-Fish-style bend). The Main Envelope
			sweeps around this.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="resonance" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Filter resonance (0-1.5). Up to 1 is the stock range — squelchy but,
			like a real 303, never quite self-oscillating; above 1 is the documented
			bend.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="envmod" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Envelope modulation (0-1): how much of the Main Envelope reaches the
			cutoff. Raising it also lowers the sweep's resting point, like the
			hardware.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="decay" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Main Envelope decay in ms (200-2000, the stock knob range). Accented
			notes bypass this and run at ~200 ms.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="accent" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Accent amount (0-1): how strongly accented notes hit — louder, with a
			faster envelope, and driving the accent-sweep circuit: consecutive accented notes
			charge a capacitor that pushes the cutoff higher note over note (the famous
			build-up, or "wow"), scaled by the resonance knob, draining away during rests. The
			sweep works even with envmod at zero, like the hardware.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="tuning" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Master tuning in cents (-1200..1200).</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="waveform" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1">
			<description>Oscillator waveform: saw or square (the hardware's two). Switching
			glides click-free.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="gain" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Output gain in dB.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="solver" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<description>Filter nonlinear solver: 0 = fast (default), 1 = exact. See
			tap.diode~.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="oversample" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<description>Filter oversampling factor (1, 2, or 4; default 2).</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="interp" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Default preset-morph time in milliseconds used by the recall message.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="smooth" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Anti-zipper interpolation time in milliseconds applied to parameter changes.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="mute" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<description>Silence the output.</description>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>


	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="tap.diode~"/>
		<seealso name="tap.vco~"/>
		<seealso name="tap.808.kick~"/>
		<seealso name="tap.adsr~"/>
	</seealsolist>


</c74object>
