<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<c74object name="tap.diode~" module="msp" category="TapTools, MSP Filters">

	<digest>
		Virtual-analog diode-ladder filter (the TB-303 topology)
	</digest>

	<description>
		The <o>tap.diode~</o> object is a virtual-analog model of the 4-pole diode-ladder
		lowpass — the filter topology of the Roland TB-303, modeled from Tim Stinchcombe's
		published circuit analysis. Unlike the buffered transistor ladder
		(<o>tap.ladder~</o>), a diode ladder's stages load each other, spreading the poles
		far apart: the response has a shallow knee near cutoff that opens into a full
		24 dB/octave slope (the honest version of the panel's famous "18 dB" claim), and the
		resonance is broad and squelchy rather than surgical. The frequency attribute is
		calibrated to the resonance peak. The resonance feedback path is high-passed
		(150 Hz, the hardware value): resonance thins as the cutoff comes down, the bass
		survives full squelch — and, exactly like a stock TB-303, the standard resonance
		range (up to 1) never quite self-oscillates. The range above 1 and the fbhp
		attribute are the documented circuit bends: extended resonance makes it sing at
		high cutoffs, and fbhp 0 converts the feedback to DC-coupled, giving exact
		self-oscillation tuning at any cutoff (with transistor-ladder-style bass droop as
		the trade). Saturating diode pairs bound everything; drive pushes the input into
		them. Runs oversampled (2x by default). A signal in the right inlet modulates the
		cutoff with true per-sample resolution. All parameters glide smoothly, and sixteen
		preset slots can be stored and morphed between. Single-channel: wrap in mc. for
		multichannel.
	</description>


	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">74 Objects</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">TapTools</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Audio</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Filter</metadata>
	</metadatalist>


	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="float">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="input" type="float" optional="0" id="0" />
			</arglist>
			<description>In the right inlet, sets the cutoff frequency in Hz.</description>
		</method>
		<method name="store">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="slot" type="int" optional="0"/>
			</arglist>
			<description>Store the current parameters in a preset slot (1-16).</description>
		</method>
		<method name="recall">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="slot" type="int" optional="0"/>
				<arg name="time" type="float" optional="1"/>
			</arglist>
			<description>
				Morph all parameters to a stored preset (1-16). The optional second argument
				overrides the morph time in milliseconds (default: the interp attribute).
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="clear">
			<arglist/>
			<description>Reset the filter state (this also stops self-oscillation).</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>


	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="frequency" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Cutoff frequency in Hz (10-20000), calibrated to the resonance peak /
			oscillation frequency. At low resonance the -3 dB point sits well below this — the
			diode ladder's spread poles, faithfully. A signal in the right inlet overrides this
			with per-sample resolution.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="resonance" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Resonance (0-1.5). 0-1 is the hardware-realistic range: squelchy, but —
			like a stock TB-303 — never quite self-oscillating. Above 1 is the documented bend:
			the filter sings at high cutoffs, bounded by the diodes. With fbhp 0 the threshold is
			exactly 1.0 and oscillation lands exactly on the cutoff.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="drive" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Input drive in dB (-24..24): how hard the signal hits the saturating
			diode pairs.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="fbhp" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Resonance-feedback high-pass corner in Hz (0-2000; default 150, the
			hardware value). This is why resonance thins toward the bass and why the low end
			survives full squelch. 0 bends the circuit to DC-coupled feedback:
			transistor-ladder behavior, exact oscillation tuning, low-end droop at high
			resonance.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="gain" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Output gain in dB.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="solver" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<description>Nonlinear solver for the coupled diode equations: 0 = fast
			(secant-linearized solve plus one corrective pass, the default), 1 = exact
			(re-linearization iterated to convergence). Audibly different only when drive and
			resonance are both pushed hard.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="oversample" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<description>Internal oversampling factor (1, 2, or 4; default 2). Higher factors
			reduce aliasing from the diode saturation, at higher CPU cost.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="interp" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Default preset-morph time in milliseconds used by the recall message.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="smooth" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Anti-zipper interpolation time in milliseconds applied to parameter changes.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="bypass" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<description>Pass the input through unprocessed.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="mute" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<description>Silence the output.</description>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>


	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="tap.ladder~"/>
		<seealso name="tap.fourpole~"/>
		<seealso name="tap.svf~"/>
		<seealso name="tap.filter~"/>
		<seealso name="lores~"/>
	</seealsolist>


</c74object>
