<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<c74object name="tap.808.kick~" module="msp" category="TapTools, MSP Synthesis">

	<digest>
		TR-808-style bass drum voice, synthesized from the analog circuit
	</digest>

	<description>
		The <o>tap.808.kick~</o> object is a circuit-informed model of the Roland TR-808 bass
		drum voice, built block for block from the original schematic (after Werner, Abel and
		Smith's DAFx-14 analysis): the pulse shaper, the bridged-T resonator with its feedback
		regeneration loop, the ~6 ms attack frequency jump that gives the drum its punch, the
		retriggering pulse, and the leakage nonlinearity behind the characteristic downward pitch
		"sigh" — all emergent from the modeled circuit rather than bolted on. Trigger it with a
		signal: a rising edge fires the voice, and the amplitude of the edge (0..1) is the accent.
		Accent is the trigger bus voltage (4-14 V on the hardware), so an accented hit excites the
		circuit harder — more punch, slightly different pitch trajectory — not merely louder.
		Filter states persist across triggers, so fast rolls interfere with the ringing tail like
		the hardware (no "machine gun effect"). The decay, tone, and level attributes mirror the
		hardware panel knobs; tuning, pulse, sigh, and attack are circuit bends beyond the panel
		(component substitutions on the modeled schematic), stock at their defaults.
		Single-channel: wrap in mc. for stacked or parallel voices.
	
		The eight tap.808 voices share one accent-bus contract; the family overview patcher (tap.808.maxhelp) demonstrates them together on a running pattern.
	</description>


	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">74 Objects</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">TapTools</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Audio</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Synthesis</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Drums</metadata>
	</metadatalist>


	<!--INLETS/OUTLETS-->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="0" type="signal">
			<digest>Trigger: a rising edge fires the voice; edge amplitude (0..1) is the accent</digest>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>
	<outletlist>
		<outlet id="0" type="signal">
			<digest>Bass drum output</digest>
		</outlet>
	</outletlist>


	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="signal">
			<arglist/>
			<description>
				A rising edge on the inlet triggers the drum, sample-accurately. The value the
				signal rises to (0..1) is the accent: it sets the trigger pulse voltage (4-14 V
				on the hardware bus), driving the circuit harder rather than scaling the output.
				A <o>click~</o>, the output of a sequencer row, or any impulse/gate works.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="bang">
			<arglist/>
			<description>
				Trigger the drum at full accent (from the scheduler; use a signal trigger for
				sample accuracy).
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="trigger">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="accent" type="float" optional="1"/>
			</arglist>
			<description>
				Trigger the drum with an accent value (0..1, default 1).
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="clear">
			<arglist/>
			<description>Reset all circuit state, silencing any ringing tail.</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>


	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="decay" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<digest>Note length (panel knob VR6)</digest>
			<description>
				Note length, 0..1 (default 0.5). The hardware decay pot in the bridged-T's
				regeneration loop: near 0 a tight thump, near 1 a note that rings for seconds —
				the classic long 808 boom.
			</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="tone" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<digest>Attack brightness (panel knob VR5)</digest>
			<description>
				Attack brightness, 0..1 (default 0.5): the passive low-pass after the resonator.
				1 keeps the click (~7 kHz corner) so the attack cuts through a mix; 0 rounds it
				off (~300 Hz).
			</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="level" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<digest>Output level (panel knob VR4)</digest>
			<description>Output level, 0..1 (default 1).</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="tuning" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<digest>Circuit bend: pitch ratio (default 1 = stock ~49 Hz)</digest>
			<description>
				Pitch as a ratio of the stock tuning, 0.25..4 (default 1). Scales the bridged-T
				arm capacitors — the component-substitution mod that makes the drum tunable. The
				stock schematic rings at about 49 Hz.
			</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="pulse" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<digest>Circuit bend: trigger pulse width in ms (default 1 = stock)</digest>
			<description>
				Trigger pulse width in milliseconds, 0.05..50 (default 1, the hardware CPU's
				pulse). Longer pulses push the excitation edges apart and change the attack.
			</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="sigh" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<digest>Circuit bend: pitch-sigh depth (default 1 = stock)</digest>
			<description>
				Depth of the characteristic downward pitch relaxation, 0..1 (default 1). 0 is the
				"disconnect the sigh" hardware mod: the note holds its pitch as it decays.
			</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="attack" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<digest>Circuit bend: attack-shift depth (default 1 = stock)</digest>
			<description>
				Depth of the ~6 ms attack frequency jump, 0..1 (default 1). This shift is where
				the drum's punch comes from — at 0 the same trigger barely couples into the
				resonator and the note collapses to a soft, quiet thud.
			</description>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>


	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="tap.adsr~"/>
		<seealso name="tap.noise~"/>
		<seealso name="tap.vco~"/>
		<seealso name="click~"/>
	</seealsolist>

</c74object>
