<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<c74object name="tap.svf~" module="msp" category="TapTools, MSP Filters">

	<digest>
		Morphing state-variable filter (Simper / zero-delay-feedback)
	</digest>

	<description>
		The <o>tap.svf~</o> object is a state-variable filter built on Andy Simper's
		trapezoidal-integration (zero-delay-feedback) SVF — the design behind the Cytomic filters
		in Ableton Live. The prewarped tuning is exact into the top octaves at any sample rate,
		and the filter stays stable under per-sample cutoff modulation (a signal in the right
		inlet). Beyond the discrete responses (lowpass, highpass, bandpass, notch, peak, allpass)
		there is a morph type that sweeps continuously around lowpass, bandpass, highpass, and
		notch — like the Morph filter in Live's Auto Filter — and parametric-EQ types (bell, low
		shelf, high shelf) with a boost/cut gain for building equalizers. The order attribute
		selects 2nd-, 4th-, or 8th-order responses (12/24/48 dB per octave) as a cascade with the
		Butterworth Q spread, so resonance 0 is maximally flat at every order and raising the
		resonance (0 to 1) sharpens a single clean peak. Two circuits are available: clean is the
		pure linear filter; driven adds an input drive into a tanh limiter on each section's band
		node, runs oversampled, and self-oscillates at the cutoff when resonance reaches 1 (give
		it a ping to start — a perfectly silent filter is a fixed point). All parameters glide
		smoothly. Single-channel: wrap in mc. for multichannel.
	</description>


	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">74 Objects</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">TapTools</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Audio</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Filter</metadata>
	</metadatalist>


	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="float">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="input" type="float" optional="0" id="0" />
			</arglist>
			<description>In the right inlet, sets the cutoff frequency in Hz.</description>
		</method>
		<method name="q">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="q" type="float" optional="1"/>
			</arglist>
			<description>
				Set the resonance attribute from a Q value (the Q of the resonant section; the
				Butterworth base Q of the current order is the minimum). Without an argument,
				posts the current equivalent Q to the Max console.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="clear">
			<arglist/>
			<description>Reset the filter state (this also stops self-oscillation).</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>


	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="type" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1">
			<description>Filter response: lowpass, highpass, bandpass, notch, peak, allpass,
			morph (continuous sweep positioned by the morph attribute), or the parametric-EQ
			types bell, lowshelf, and highshelf (boost/cut set by the gain attribute; the EQ
			types always run 2nd-order).</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="frequency" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Cutoff / center frequency in Hz (1-20000). A signal in the right inlet
			overrides this with per-sample resolution.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="resonance" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Resonance (0-1). 0 is maximally flat (Butterworth); rising values sharpen
			a single resonant peak. At 1 the clean circuit reaches a very high finite Q; the
			driven circuit self-oscillates at the cutoff. Use the q message to set this from a Q
			value.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="morph" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Position around the response circle when type is morph: 0 = lowpass,
			0.25 = bandpass, 0.5 = highpass, 0.75 = notch, 1 wraps back to lowpass. The corners
			are identical to the discrete types.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="gain" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Boost/cut in dB (-24..24) for the parametric-EQ types (bell, lowshelf,
			highshelf); ignored by the other types.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="drive" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Input drive in dB (-24..24) into the driven circuit's saturation;
			ignored by the clean circuit.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="circuit" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1">
			<description>clean: the pure linear SVF (transparent, cheap, no oversampling).
			driven: adds drive into a tanh limiter on each section's band node — saturation
			color, bounded resonance, true self-oscillation at resonance 1 — and runs
			oversampled.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="order" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<description>Filter order: 2, 4, or 8 (12/24/48 dB per octave), as a cascade with the
			Butterworth Q spread — resonance 0 stays maximally flat at every order. The EQ types
			always run 2nd-order.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="oversample" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<description>Internal oversampling factor for the driven circuit (1, 2, or 4; default
			2). Reduces aliasing from the saturation. The clean circuit is linear and always runs
			1x.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="smooth" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<description>Anti-zipper interpolation time in milliseconds applied to parameter changes.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="bypass" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<description>Pass the input through unprocessed.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="mute" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<description>Silence the output.</description>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>


	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="tap.ladder~"/>
		<seealso name="tap.fourpole~"/>
		<seealso name="tap.filter~"/>
		<seealso name="svf~"/>
		<seealso name="biquad~"/>
	</seealsolist>


</c74object>
